Tufts Medical Center Records UA144
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Medical Center Records
1911 -- 1998
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Tufts Medical Center
UA144
6.1 Linear Feet 9 boxes
Arrangement
This collection is organized into two series: Subject files and Unprocessed accessions.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains correspondence, newspaper clippings, photographs, publications, reports, and subject files relating to the founding and operations of the Tufts Medical Center, formerly known as Tufts New England Medical Center. Other topics significantly represented in this collection include the Boston Dispensary and the Bingham Associates Fund of Massachusetts.
Biographical / Historical
The New England Medical Center (NEMC) is the principal teaching hospital for the School of Medicine and School of Dental Medicine. The Medical Center's chiefs of service are joint appointees with the medical school and most serve as chairs of their respective departments at the medical school. Students take 25% of their required third year clerkships and 50% of their fourth year electives at NEMC.
Recognizing that education and research are essential components to good medical care, the New England Medical Center was established in 1930 through the alliance of the Boston Dispensary, the Boston Floating Hospital for Infants and Children, and the Trustees of Tufts College. The NEMC was established as a non-profit corporation to coordinate the administrative activities of its constituent organizations. In 1946 the Joseph H. Pratt Diagnostic Hospital, an extension of the Boston Dispensary established in 1938, joined NEMC. In 1950, when the Medical School and Dental School relocated to Harrison Avenue, the NEMC became known as the New England Medical Center Hospital.
The entity was renamed Tufts-New England Medical Center in 1968, and in 1970 the NEMC board met at the Coonamessett Inn in Falmouth, Massachusetts to outline ways the NEMC and Tufts could further coordinate operations. The resulting directives, known as the Coonamessett Statement, indicated that support services and other business functions should be made the responsibility of T-NEMC in each case where it made sense to do so. That same year Tufts President Hallowell and NEMC President Quarles signed an affiliation agreement that codified the T-NEMC as an alliance through which its constituent units would move toward a completely integrated operation. By 1976, T-NEMC controlled health care studies, medical engineering, community health and ambulatory care, employee-student health services, lab animal medicine, some research, off-site medical services, a common utility supply center, architectural services, communications, educational media, parking facilities, property ownership, and public relations. However, by the late 1970s both institutions had experienced a change in leadership, resulting in a change of priorities for each. Interest in integration waned and the cooperation forged in the early 1970s was dismantled.
After a period of tension and competition in the 1980s, Tufts and NEMC drafted a new affiliation agreement in 1991, which remains in effect as of 1999. In 2000, the center was once again named Tufts-New England Medical Center, or T-NEMC.
Conditions Governing Access
University records are closed for 20 years from the date of their creation. Records older than 20 years that do not pertain to student education, staff and faculty employment and Board of Trustees records are open for research. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Centers and Institutes; Facilities; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material; Curriculum and Instruction -- Faculty
- Subject Files, 1911 -- 1985; UA144.001; 1.75 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  The "Subject Files" series in the NEMC collection was created by Russell Miller while preparing Light on the Hill, his history of Tufts College. It contains material relating to general NEMC matters that did not fit into any of his other subject categories. The material was assembled from various administrative departments. No attempt has been made to restore the original order of this material.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - NEMC: General, 1930 -- 1950; UA144.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Bingham Associates, 1946 -- 1958; UA144.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Bingham Associates, 1930 -- 1947; UA144.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Bingham Associates, 1940 -- 1972; UA144.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Bingham Associates, Minutes, 1946 -- 1955; UA144.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Board Meetings, 1929 -- 1932; UA144.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Boston Dispensary, 1913 -- 1977; UA144.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - NEMC: Boston Floating Hospital, 1941 -- 1979; UA144.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Center Capers, 1965; UA144.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Clinics and Services, 1970; UA144.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Community Health and Ambulatory Care, 1977; UA144.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Community Relations, 1938 -- 1982; UA144.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Fund Raising, 1929 -- 1930; UA144.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Fund Raising, 1930 -- 1931; UA144.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - NEMC: Fund Raising, 1930; UA144.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Fund Raising Survey, 1964; UA144.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Grounds and Buildings, 1963 -- 1973; UA144.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Hinsey Report, 1958 -- 1959; UA144.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Hospital Annual Reports, 1964 -- 1982; UA144.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Hospital, 1959 -- 1974; UA144.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Integration Committee, 1961 -- 1965; UA144.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Personnel, 1959 -- 1981; UA144.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Pratt Clinic, 1939 -- 1963; UA144.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Public Relations Report, 1965; UA144.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - NEMC: Recreation Facilities, 1967; UA144.001.004.00001 (Box 4)
  - NEMC: Rehabilitation Training Center, 1980 -- 1985; UA144.001.004.00002 (Box 4)
  - NEMC: Tremont Dispensary, 1911 -- 1912; UA144.001.004.00003 (Box 4)
  - NEMC: Wolfe, George A., 1956 -- 1966; UA144.001.004.00004 (Box 4)
- Additional accessions, UA144.000034
  - New England Medical Center (NEMC): H.H. Fields Files, UA144-021 (Box data_value_missing_288c7f3497ccbf049ccbffc78cf0b56c, Box 1)
    20 years from date of creation.
  - New England Medical Center (NEMC): H.H. Fields Files, UA144-022 (Box data_value_missing_288c7f3497ccbf049ccbffc78cf0b56c, Box 2)
  - Publications, T-NEMC Newsletter and History, UA144-023 (Box data_value_missing_945ebf3516521c1d61400f80b6cd194b, Box 3)
  - NEMC-Boston Street Photos; H.H. Fields, UA144-026 (Box data_value_missing_10aab0dac3deb3fb99135f48d7c0114d, Box 4)
  - NEMC - newsletters, guides, and reports, 1976 -- 1998; UA144-027 (Box data_value_missing_6d83bccf6ad7cf85d0fee318f5a18cdc, Box 5)